בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is דף ס', Daf Samach,
60, and we pick up where we from the very bottom of
נ"ט עמוד ב'. Nun Tet amud bet. Just review what we picked
up yesterday, first of all, just in as an upshot of a
lot of the discussions we've been having about squaring off cities, I
mentioned to you the חזון איש Chazon Ish addresses the issue that
if after you've squared off a city, the square overlaps with another
city, it's all considered to be one, which is basically critically important
so that basically merges Manhattan with
the Bronx with New Jersey with Queens and Brooklyn and so on,
because those squares overlap even though even
though they otherwise are not contiguous. That's just a point, an important
halachic point. But anyway, what we've been talking about more immediately is
this whole idea of a private city becoming public and a public
becoming private where רש"י Rashi says it has to do with the
600,000 people, the potential for רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim. The רמב"ן Ramban
agrees it has to do with the potential for רשות הרבים, Reshut
Harabim, but he reads it very narrowly in terms of the issue
of ownership. That it has to be owned by the רבים rabim
or at least the streets do, and he is very skeptical about
the 600,000 criteria. Thank you. So what is the relevance of that
for us? Well,
the משנה Mishna said two things. It said that if it started
off as public, that identity still sticks with it even if it
became private. And that means that in order to make it clear
that this has the potential for רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim and so
on, you cannot make you cannot make you have to leave over
a section that you have not made an עירוב eruv for with.
The way the some explained that is is that first of all
you could say that symbolizes the fact that it's not a unified
place, it's not a single place, it's a place of masses. But
also it reminds people of the existence of עירוב. eruv. You know,
there's some people that are of the position that once a year
a city that has an עירוב eruv should take down its עירוב,
eruv, should not use it in order to remind people that there's
such a מלאכה melacha in the תורה Torah called carrying.
They used to on Wednesdays used to do that in Manhattan.
Alright, so the way that some explain it is is that if
it's a city that started off of the רבים, rabim, it has
more of this identity even though now it might not have that
and therefore you want there to be an area you can't carry
in. So if you leave off a section, even if that section
makes its own עירוב eruv and you have your own עירוב, eruv,
but you can't carry from section A to section B of the
city. So that the part of that point is to, you know,
remind you of the issue of רשות הרבים, Reshut Harabim, whereas if
it started off של יחיד shel yachid even though now it's רבים,
rabim, although that's ironic because now potentially it could have a רשות
הרבים Reshut Harabim also, we have less we don't have that concern
and quite the opposite, the משנה mishna says that in that case
you're supposed to make a unified עירוב. eruv. It has more of
the identity of being an individual and any potentially shared space is
potentially problematic as we spoke about yesterday and therefore they're all supposed
to make an עירוב eruv together. So that was basically the principles
with one final issue, sorry, with one final issue being
that
a city that was of the רבים rabim and maybe still is
of the רבים rabim and so on, it might be more complicated
to make an עירוב eruv around a רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim because
since it's genuinely a רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim then, you know, the
idea that you can just put like a צורת הפתח tzurat hapetach
or a לחי lechi and a קורה kora is less obvious and
the גמרא Gemara yesterday discussed the need for for one of the
ends to be a dead end. Okay, so there are all of
those differences: A, doing everything together or leaving off, and B, whether
you can actually make an עירוב eruv around רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim.
So let's now with that with that in mind pick up a
little bit back from where we did yesterday with בעי מיניה רב
אמי בר אדא הרכנא מרבה. Ba'ei minei Rav Ami bar Ada harcha
n'a miRabba. So it is the eighth line from the bottom, sixth
line before the lines get wide. Okay, so here's what he asked
רבה: Rabba: סולם מכאן ופתח מכאן. sulam mikan upetach mikan.
Let's say this רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim one side is open and
one side is not totally dead-ended, it's got a wall but there's
a ladder on the wall. Okay, so מהו, mahu, what's the story?
Is that like a full רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim that you can't
make an עירוב eruv around it, again based on whether it's a
private-public city, or is it not? אמר ליה הכי אמר רב, amar
lei hachi amar Rav, סולם תורת פתח עליו. sulam torat petach alav.
A ladder makes it like it's an opening and therefore it's problematic,
it's an open-ended רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim. So אמר ליה רב נחמן,
amar lei Rav Nachman, so רב נחמן Rav Nachman said, לא תשמעיה,
lo tishme'ei, don't listen to him. הכי אמר רב אדא בר אהבה
אמר רב, hachi amar Rav Ada bar Ahava amar Rav, here's what
רב אדא Rav Ada said in the name of רב, Rav, again
to a different version of what רב Rav said, סולם תורת פתח
עליו ותורת מחיצה עליו. sulam torat petach alav v'torat mechitza alav. You
didn't get the whole story. רב Rav didn't just say it was
a פתח, petach, he said it's sometimes a פתח, petach, sometimes a
מחיצה. mechitza. So it's got a wall but it's got a ladder.
So sometimes it's a wall, sometimes it's an opening.
ותורת מחיצה עליו, v'torat mechitza alav, it's a wall for what purposes?
כמאן דאמר k'man d'amar like we said that if you've got a
wall with a ladder on it, it makes it considered to be
a not an open-ended רשות הרבים. Reshut Harabim. It makes it considered
to be effectively enough of a closed-ended רשות הרבים Reshut Harabim that
it's possible to make an עירוב eruv around it. So that's being
lenient. And תורת פתח עליו, torat petach alav, it's considered an opening
for what purposes? בסולם שבין שתי חצרות. besulam shebein shtei chatzerot.
If you have a ladder between two courtyards... between two courtyards, meaning
a wall between courtyards, but they are but you can get over
the wall with a ladder. רצו אחד מערבין רצו שניים מערבין. ratzu
echad me'arvin ratzu shnayim me'arvin. If you want they can make one,
if one עירוב, eruv, if you want they can make two. So
what that is,
if you have here, you have
two courtyards, okay?
If they are totally open to one another, effectively they're one. And
if this one cannot make an עירוב eruv by itself because if
it did, it's half of the courtyard making an עירוב, eruv, and
you can't have that. Let's say you had, let's say you had
I don't know an entire wall, then they can't make an עירוב
eruv together because they're not one. So each courtyard has to make
its own עירוב. eruv. However, let's say there's a doorway. Then they
can consider themselves one, and if they want they can make a
unified עירוב. eruv. They can consider themselves two and they can make
an individual עירוב. eruv. So if you have a wall with a
ladder, that's the same as a doorway. You can consider yourselves one,
you can consider yourselves two, it works like a פתח. petach. So
a ladder can work like a פתח petach to for sometimes, to
be lenient to allow you to unify if you want to unify.
And it also serves like a wall, the wall and the ladder,
if to be lenient so that a רשות הרבים reshut harabbim that
ends with a wall with a ladder is considered to be a
non-open-ended רשות הרבים. reshut harabbim.
So does it make a difference which side the ladder's on? Only
on one side, it can't really...
Oh yeah, that's a good point. It would have to be two
sides, or this would have to be on a higher level or
something.
Yeah, the picture book has two sides.
Good point. Okay.
Also he has this expression 'don't listen to him' too. That's unusual,
right? Like don't listen to him? But I think because they're...
Well they're arguing about what רב Rav actually had said.
Whose father, who he's
like, don't listen
to what רב Rav says, because your tradition, your father רב אדא...
Rav Adda...
Oh that's interesting. Your father actually has a different tradition in the
name of רב. Rav. I hadn't noticed that, that's a good point.
So maybe that's why he's being so emphatic. Okay, very good point.
So now the גמרא Gemara says like this: ומי אמר רב נחמן
הכי? Umi amar Rav Nachman hachi? Did רב נחמן Rav Nachman really
say that? That you can go either way? האמר רב נחמן אמר
שמואל. Ha'amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel. רב נחמן Rav Nachman said in
the name of שמואל: Shmuel: אנשי חצר ואנשי מרפסת. Anshei chatzer ve'anshei
mirpesset.
People of a courtyard and people of a balcony, like a מרפסת,
mirpesset, ששכחו. sheshachechu. You know,
the best way to imagine this is I think like at those
motels, you know, where they have, you know, where they've got basically,
you know, they have all those units and then on the second
floor, you know, there's that whole walk around and that whole balcony
sticking out to a courtyard. So the bottom unit are the people
of the courtyard, and the top unit are the people of the
balcony. And they also want to go down to the courtyard and
use the courtyard. So is that like one big חצר, chatzer, right?
Because you have all these different units. Or are the people who
use the balcony and then go down into the courtyard, are they
distinct in terms of this issue? So, if the people ששכחו ולא
עירבו. sheshachechu velo eirvu. They forgot and they did not make a
unified courtyard, meaning a unified עירוב. eruv. The people on the bottom
floor made an עירוב, eruv, and the people on the top made
an עירוב, eruv, but they are all going to use the חצר.
chatzer. They're all going to go down to the חצר. chatzer. So
they didn't make an עירוב eruv together. אם יש לפניהם דקה ארבעה
אין אוסרת במאי עסקינן. Im yesh lifneichem daka arba'ah ein osseret bimai
askinan.
So this is again this idea of a little barrier of four
טפחים, tefachim, which is interesting. Normally barriers are ten טפחים tefachim or
nothing. But we have this before, that that's enough to set apart
one segment from another in terms of this issue. Like we said,
if a house had this, or a courtyard had this, it's not
part of the מבוי. mavoi. The idea that everybody has to be
together or it's nothing. If you set yourself apart from the public
space with this little barrier, you're able to be out of the
picture. So if the people from above put a little barrier, you
know, let's say on the stairs that go down, in front of,
on the top of the stairs, on the landing of the stairs,
they have cut themselves off from the courtyard, and then it's okay.
Then the people of the bottom level can all be together. Okay?
Is that clear? Now the question is though, what's the access of
the people of the top to the bottom? It's by a ladder.
Okay, we would think steps, but it's by a ladder. So if
a ladder you have can be considered a מחיצה, mechitzah, then who
needs, right, this little barrier? You already have a wall with a
ladder and that should be enough of a barrier.
Okay? So is that clear? You've got here all the people who
are in these units up here, and
then the people who are in the units down there, and here's
the courtyard, okay? And here is the ladder that lets them get
down to the courtyard. So if a, if the need to go
over a ladder is effectively considered, could be considered a wall, could
be a פתח, petach, you have your choice. So fine, just consider
it to be a wall. Or you know, you could even say
further, even if you consider it to be a פתח, petach, it
should be, we say a פתח petach you don't have to all
be together. So these should be able to be separate from these.
Why did I have to make a barrier in order to separate
themselves out? Why isn't the fact that the only access is by
a ladder enough to allow them to be separate either, you know,
even as a פתח petach but certainly as a מחיצה? mechitzah? So
that's the question. So the גמרא Gemara says הכא במאי עסקינן, Hacha
bimai askinan, what are we talking about here?
בדלא גבוה מרפסת עשרה. bidlo gavoah mirpeset asarah. It is a very
low balcony, one wonders how you construct this without crushing the people
below, but anyways, the balcony is less than ten טפחים tefachim off
of the courtyard. So somehow, I really don't know how this exactly
operates, maybe the other people's access is this way, this access and
like this, okay, and this balcony goes down like that. What you
have to do so you don't collapse, anyway, whatever it is, okay.
So anyway they go and they use this balcony here and they
are less than ten טפחים tefachim off of the ground and then
you've got then you jump down you get a ladder to get
you down. Okay, so in this case where the people here are
less than ten טפחים tefachim off the ground then they then the
issue of wall ladder is irrelevant, they're considered to be on the
ground. Okay, so it's a very special case. Obviously it's the ברייתא
baraita sounds like it's talking about all cases but we're saying it's
a very special case, they're really not, you know, it's not a
מחיצה mechitza with a ladder, less than עשרה asarah is nothing. So
they're effectively considered on the ground. Like let's see the answer. So
the גמרא Gemara says, בדלא גבוה מרפסת עשרה. bidlo gavoah mirpeset asarah.
אי לא גבוה מרפסת עשרה, ee lo gavoah mirpeset asarah, if it's
not ten high, so says the גמרא, Gemara, if that's true where
am I אי לא גבוה מרפסת עשרה ee lo gavoah mirpeset asarah
כי
קא עביד דקא מאי הוי? ki ka avid daka mai havei? So
who cares if you make a little barrier, right? I mean why
should that matter? Now, you know,
so it's basically it says it's completely open, meaning so so what
if you make a barrier here or a barrier here, right, if
all of this is within עשרה טפחים asarah tefachim all around the
sides, right, a barrier does help to cut off a house if
it if it completely is in front of the whole opening. Okay,
so maybe if you made the entire thing a דקא daka you'd
be okay, but maybe the גמרא Gemara could have answered that, but
it assumes you're only making it by the ladder. So why does
it help? You're basically considered straight in the courtyard. Okay,
so let's see what the answer is. So it says
where were we
הכא במאי עסקינן hacha b'mai askinan where were we בדלא גבוה מרפסת
עשרה אי לא גבוה מרפסת עשרה כי קא עביד דקא מאי הוי?
bidlo gavoah mirpeset asarah ee lo gavoah mirpeset asarah ki ka avid
daka mai havei? במגופפת עד עשר אמות. bim'gufefet ad eser amot. No,
because what we're talking about here is is that there's actually a
wall around it up until with a ten אמה amah break. דכיון
דעביד דקא אסתלוקי אסתלק ליה מהכא. d'keivan d'avid daka istalokei istalak lei
mehacha. And therefore once you make the barrier you've removed yourself. So
the גמרא's Gemara basic answer, right, is that the גמרא's Gemara basic
answer is that you basically have here, you already have a wall,
I hope you do or else you'd fall off the balcony or
something. Okay, so you've got already a wall there. This space is
עשר אמות. eser amot. Up to now up
any space that's עשר אמות eser amot or bigger is not considered
a פתח, petach, it's considered as if it's completely open. Right? We
said before a small opening is a פתח petach and you could
consider yourself separate. But עשר אמות eser amot is already a break
and not a פתח. petach. And therefore if you make a little
barrier here you basically have effectively shortened the עשר אמות eser amot
and therefore you're back to it being a פתח petach and therefore
that's why you're able to be separate. So the real problem is
is that this ברייתא baraita sounds like it's talking, I mean the
גמרא Gemara does this all the time but okay, this ברייתא baraita
sounds like it's talking about every single case about a courtyard and
a balcony and we said
we're talking about a very special case, the balcony is within ten
of the ground, there basically is a barrier around it except for
a ten אמה amah opening and therefore that's why it's all a
problem and that's why this little additional barrier helps. All right. דכיון
דעביד להו דקא אסתלוקי אסתלק ליה מהכא, d'keivan d'avid lehu daka istalokei
istalak lei mehacha, once you made this barrier
then you have removed yourself from the courtyard. Michael you had a
question before?
My question was just we were talking about sorry to go back
a moment for overlapping תחום. tchum. Does political realities have anything to
do with it? Like let's say one is New York, one is
New Jersey and they're different states, you know, different cities?
Yeah, no, because when the גמרא Gemara speaks about two cities being
within two hundred feet, 141 אמות, amot,
it's completely unrelated if they're under different, you know, controls and whatever
so those are not relevant. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues.
Okay,
now we're going to actually do this almost almost again in a
different version. אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל: Amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel:
כותל שרצפו בסולמות. kotel sheritzo b'sulamot.
Let's say you have a wall that you completely made, you know,
ladders all over, you know, completely in all parts of the wall.
אפילו ביתר מעשר תורת מחיצה עליו. afilu b'yeter m'eser torat mechitza alav.
Even more than ten אמות, amot, it still is considered a מחיצה.
mechitza. What does that mean? It means that I just got through
telling you, okay we've got our map again, you had your two
courtyards, and I just got through telling you that if you had
a break here that was עשר אמות, eser amot, right, eleven אמה,
amah, that they're considered one courtyard. Anything more than ten is considered
one. Let's say you didn't have a... break. Let's say what you
had is you had a straight wall, but you had ladders going
for a continuous 11 אמות. amos. Okay? Right?
So he says that doesn't matter. Again, because of the wall, even
though there's a ladder, if it was a total break, it would
be considered one space. Because of the wall with ladders, it could
also be considered a מחיצה, mechitza, so it is not considered one
space even if it is more than 10 אמות. amos. Okay, so
it says like this, תורת מחיצה. Toras Mechitza. So רמי ליה Rami
lei רב ברונא Rav Bruna לרב יהודה le-Rav Yehuda במצרתא דבי רב
חנינא. be-matzarta de-bei Rav Chanina.
So we've had that once before. So that Rav Bruna asked Rav
Yehuda a contradiction when they were in the pressing floor, the like,
you know, the, I think it's where they press olives, in the
house of Rabbi Chanina. We had this once before this discussion. There
they are, they're in the olive floor, you know, maybe that's where
they had the ישיבה, yeshiva, like maybe it was not during season,
it was a big nice open space to use, maybe they were
all just out and working in the olives and they happened to
be talking תורה Torah as they were working. But anyway, that's where
they were. So מי אמר שמואל תורת מחיצה לאו? mi amar Shmuel
Toras Mechitza lav? Does Shmuel really say that it can still count
as a wall? והאמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל ve-amar Rav Nachman amar
Shmuel אנשי מרפסת ואנשי חצר, anshei mirpesset ve-anshei chatzer,
so exact same question, it's going to be the exact same answer.
And didn't we say this issue about the people with the balcony
and the people of the courtyard ששכחו ולא עירבו? she-shachachu velo eirvu?
They did not make a unified עירוב. eiruv. אם יש לפניה דקה
ארבעה אינו אוסר, im yesh lifneha daka arba'ah eino oser, if you
have a little, a little barrier, then they're separate and they don't
make forbidden on one another, ואם לאו אוסר, ve-im lav oser, and
otherwise they do forbid on one another. So therefore you see that
even with the, that
with
the, that with the ladder, it still is considered to effectively be
one place or, and it's a problem, and it's not considered a
מחיצה. mechitza. So the גמרא Gemara says, הכא במאי עסקינן דלא גבה
מרפסת עשרה, hacha mai askinan delo gavah mirpesset asara, the balcony is
not 10 off the ground and therefore it's not a wall with
a ladder, it's basically as if it's not a wall at all,
it's like they're all together. ואי לא גבה מרפסת עשרה, ve-ei lo
gavah mirpesset asara, כי עביד דקה מאי הוה? ki avid daka mai
hava?
And if it's not then, so then how does this little barrier
help if they're all one place? So we're going to say, במגופפת
עד עשרה אמות, bi-megufefet ad asara amos, because it is surrounded by
a wall up with a
10 אמה amah break, וכיון דעביד דקה ve-kivan de-avid daka אשתלוקי אשתלוק
מהכא. ishtalukei ishtaluk mehacha.
You've removed yourself. So okay, a repeat of the whole idea. Anyway,
this is one question about a wall with a ladder, which although
there was seems to be evidence against this by this discussion about
the balcony, about the people of the balcony, nevertheless the גמרא's Gemara
position is that a wall with a ladder you can use either
way לקולא, lekula, either as a פתח petach or as a wall.
At one place רש"י Rashi says it's because in general we go
לקולא lekula by עירובין. eiruvin. You could have said that it's not
because we go לקולא, lekula, you could have just said that by
its nature it's more of a hybrid reality and therefore has features
of both. But anyway, that is the issue about the wall with
the ladder. Now the גמרא Gemara gets back to a very interesting
fun little story about this idea of having to, if it's an
עיר של רבים, ir shel rabim, having to do, you know, not
make an עירוב eiruv around the entire city. So let's take a
look.
הנהו בני כקונאי, Hanu benei Kakunai, the people of Kakunai, some village
or whatever, or city, דאתו לקמיה דרב יוסף, de-asu lekamei de-Rav Yosef,
came to Rav
Yosef. אמרי ליה, amrei lei, הבו לן גברא דליערב לן מאתא, hav
lan gavra deli-eirev lan masta, you know, could you get send for
us a guy that will make an עירוב eiruv around our city?
Okay? It's like same things happens today, I need a rabbi to
come in and help me make an עירוב. eiruv. So they went
to Rav Yosef and said, give us one of your students to
help us make an עירוב. eiruv. אמר ליה לאביי, amar lei le-Abaye,
so Rav Yosef said to Abaye, זיל עירב להו, zil eirev lehu,
go make an עירוב eiruv for them, וחזי, ve-chazi, and pay attention,
like take heed, דלא מצווחי עלך delo metzavchu alach בבי מדרשא, be-bei
midrasha, that they don't yell about it in the בית מדרש, beis
medrash, meaning you know, make sure that it's kosher and as we're
going to see, but don't make undue חומרות chumras about it and
drive them crazy so they're going to have something to complain about.
Okay? So do it right, pay attention to do it right. I
want to also by the way repeat that here we are seeing
more and more the verb of עירב, eirev, עירוב eiruv mean the
entire enterprise of, you know, of making it all work. Now again,
it could be that he didn't have to make walls, we'll see,
it could all be just about the bread together, but it's clearly
more than just about the bread, it's about all the details that
are required to make it that you can carry there. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says, אזל, azal,
so Abaye went, חזא להנהו בתי דפתיחי לנהרא. chaza le-hanei batei de-ptichi
lenahara. So the basic issue here is going to be that it
was an עיר של רבים ir shel rabim and he had to
leave a section off. Okay? So the question is which section to
leave off? Because if you leave a section off, by the way,
what about those people? Okay, so that's going to be his issue,
which section to leave off. So he saw that there were certain
houses that opened to a river on a side of the city,
but presumably did not open into the city itself. Okay, maybe they
had boats and that's how, you know, whatever, but it didn't open
into the city itself. So אמר, amar, good, הני ליהוו שיורא למאתא,
hanei le-havei shiyura le-masta,
let these be the part of the city I'm not making an
עירוב eiruv around since anyway they don't go out of their house
into the city, they go out of their house in the, you
know, the back door. into the river, so נשקפי לך, Nishkafei lach,
they won't be able to carry right within the city. Okay, that's
the easiest, we'll leave these guys off. So הדר אמר, Hadar amar,
then he said, wait, אין מערבין את כולה תנן, Ein me'arvin et
kullah tnan, the Mishnah says you can't make an עירוב eruv for
the entire city of an עיר של רבים, ir shel rabbim, מכלל
mikhla
which implies דבעלי עירובי מצו מערבי, de-ba'alei eruvi matzi me'arvei, that if
you wanted to, you could have made them. You have to leave
off a section that otherwise you could have included. That's a reasonable
read of the Mishnah, right? Not leave off a section that can't
be included. You have to leave off a section that otherwise could
be included. So the fact is these people, even if I wanted
to, I couldn't include them because they are not, they don't have
an opening into the public space of the city. So they can't
be included in the עירוב eruv the same way you can't include
people of a different courtyard, even though the back of their houses
are part of the city, their houses don't open into the city.
So this is not considered leaving over; I couldn't include them anyway.
אלא אי עביד להו כיבי דאי בעו למערבי דרך חלונות מצי מערבי.
Ella i avid lehu kivei de-ei ba'u le-arvei derekh khalonot matzi me'arvei.
Ah, here's a way. 'Cause he still wanted to leave these guys
off, because least harm is if these guys are left out of
the city, so out of the עירוב. eruv. So here's what I'll
do: I'll have them make windows in their back walls which open
into the public space of the city, okay? And therefore in theory
they are members of the city now because they could go through
the window and, was that Beatles song, She Came in Through the
Bathroom Window or something, anyway, they could go through the
window, but you know, it's easier to exclude them 'cause basically that's
not the real way they're going to get in and out of
their house. So they don't lose too much by being excluded. But
the fact that they have a window means that they are potentially
includable, and therefore it works to leave them off.
Not to be a practical entrance?
Right, presumably. Okay, so that was that was his next brilliant idea.
But then he said, הדר אמר, Hadar amar, then he said, now
obviously you understand because if you don't want them yelling at you,
so you don't want the people of the city yelling at you
that you didn't let some of them be part of the עירוב.
eruv. So that's why you want these guys to be the ones
excluded. But on the other hand, you don't want these guys yelling
at you that you made them make a window in their back
wall of their house. So הדר אמר, Hadar amar, then he said,
you know what? לא בעי, Lo ba'ei, I really don't have to
make a window. Why? דרב בר אבוה מערב לה לכולה מחוזא אריסייתא
אריסייתא. De-Rav bar Avuha me'arev lah le-khullah Mechuza arisyata arisyata. Rav bar
Avuha made an עירוב eruv of all of מחוזא, Mechuza, each
sort of
each like street by itself, משום פירא דבי תורי, mishum peira de-vei
tori,
because of the, there was these, they kept fruit for the cattle
between the streets in these, in these ditches between the streets, there's
a nice little picture of רש״י Rashi on... דכל חדא וחדא הוי
שיור לחברתה, de-kol chada ve-chada havei shiyur le-chavertah, and every one of
them was considered a שיור shiyur for its friend, which means basically,
I mean, there's a basic picture in רש״י. Rashi. Here you have
a city, okay? It's got different, little, like neighborhoods, imagine, right? And
each one has its own streets or whatever. Okay, and in between
the neighborhoods is where they keep all of this in these, in
these ditches, all of this food for the oxen. Okay, so he
basically said, look, here's what I'm going to do. Now this is
an עיר של רבים. ir shel rabbim. So I'll make this have
an עירוב eruv and this one have an עירוב eruv and this
one have an עירוב eruv and this one have an עירוב. eruv.
So the Mishnah that said an עיר של רבים ir shel rabbim
you can't make it all an עירוב, eruv, it meant you can't
make it all one עירוב, eruv, but you can make separate עירובים
eruvin for different sections. And that's the phrase כל חדא וחדא הוי
שיור לחברתה, kol chada ve-chada havei shiyur le-chavertah, each one, this one
is the part not being מערב me'urav for these guys, and this
one is the part not being מערב me'urav for the other guys.
So the basic point being that as long as it's not a
unified עירוב. eruv. Again, the way I think the מהרש״א Maharsha explains
it is since you can't carry from here to here, from here
to here, it reminds you of the problem of carrying even though
you can fully carry within your own עירוב. eruv. Okay, so he
said, now why is that relevant? Okay, so let's see why that's
relevant. So he so what's relevant is ואף על גב דאי
בעו לערובי בהדי הדדי לא מצו מערבי. ve-af al gav de-ei ba'u
le-arvei bahadi hadadei lo matzi me'arvei. Ah, but here look, there was
there would have been no way to have made this all one
עירוב eruv even if you would have want, why? Why could you
not make it one עירוב? eruv? Because of all the big ditches
with all of this animal food, basically you cannot consider them all
unified. Those ditches are like big walls between them, okay? A ditch
is the same as a wall. And therefore we said before if
A and B are separated by a wall you can't make a
unified עירוב. eruv. Okay, so he said, this teaches me that you
can consider something the part left off even if it's a part
that I couldn't have made part of a unified עירוב. eruv. So
no problem leaving off the people in the house, in the houses
opening to the river. Wait wait, let's just finish this. Okay. Okay,
so so now he's got it, great, so we're back to where
we started. We're going to use the people whose house opens to
the river. I'm not going to have to have them make windows
in their back in in you know in their on their back
wall because even though they couldn't in theory... it could be included,
it's still considered that they're a section of the city that's excluded.
Okay, הדר אמר לא
דמי.
Hadar amar
lo dami. Then he said, wait, one minute, that's not a good
comparison. התם. Hasam. You see how hard he was thinking. He was
told that he better do it right. Okay, so התם, Hasam, well,
התם Hasam איבעי ליה ערובי דרך גגות ibai lei eruvei derech gagot
והני לא מערבי. ve-hani lo me'arvi. He says, no, no, no. The
reason here it worked was although you've got these ditches, but in
theory, like he says, there was overhang of the roofs, and you
could have, the reason you could consider them, you could have made
one big עירוב, Eruv, this because you could access from one set
of roofs to the other set of roofs. And therefore they are
considered to be, you know, the ditches don't fully separate them out.
So we're back to the problem that if a section is considered
fully separate and cannot be part of the עירוב, Eruv, it also
can't be part of the שיור shiur of the part left over.
Okay, so we're back to having to make windows in these guys'
houses.
Where were we? הלכך נעבדין פתחי. Hilkach na'avidin pitchi. So
we therefore we have to make these windows. הדר אמר, Hadar amar,
then he went and said, כיון דנמי לא בעי, Kivan nami lo
bai, you know what? We don't need the windows. דההוא בית תבנא
דהוה ליה למר בר פפידותא, D'hahu beit tivna d'hava lei le-Mar bar
Papidutsa,
there was a certain grain, you know, house of grain, a storage,
a grain storage facility that this person had, בפומבדיתא, bi-Pumbedita, ושביה שיורא
לפומבדיתא, ve-shavyei shiyura le-Pumbedita,
and that was the place that they left over for פומבדיתא. Pumbedita.
So basically you had פומבדיתא, Pumbedita, you had this big עיר של
רבים, Ir shel rabbim, you had this one guy that he had
here, you know, so here you have your entire city, whatever you
have, and then you have this one guy and he had his
little, he had his little, you know, grain house there in the
corner and they said, okay, we'll just exclude the grain house. So
now even if, so therefore, so you see you can exclude a
place that otherwise, you know, really can't be included. It's a grain
house, it's not a place where, it's not a place where people
live. So you see you can exclude a place that anyway could
not have been, could not have been what, or bigger.
Remember Rabbi Shimon said it has to be שלוש חצרות של שני
בתים. shalosh chatzerot shel sheni batim.
Right. So that is a good point. So תוספות Tosafot discusses it
and other ראשונים Rishonim discuss it and they basically say you have
to assume that first of all that it was one of the
three. First of all, you have to assume what about the fact
that you need בתים. batim. So they say it has to be
assumed that there was a little domicile that was attached to it,
you know, sort of like we had the domicile attached to the
bridge and attached to the graveyard and so on. How about the
fact that you need three? So we're going to see in a
minute in the גמרא Gemara there's an opinion you only need one,
or if you needed three it was one of the three. Okay.
So, but yes, it was one of the things that was excluded.
And so what do we do? Wait, wait, no, let's finish this.
Okay. So, אמר
היינו דאמר לי מר,
Amar hainu d'amar li
Mar,
that's must be what the master said to me, that היינו דאמר
לי מר hainu d'amar li Mar חזי דלא מצפחא לך בבי מדרשא,
chazi d'lo mitzapcha lach be-vei midrasha, make sure that they don't yell
about me, about, yell about in the בית מדרש, Beis Medrash, because,
you know, A, that, A, it worked and B, you didn't exclude
people that didn't need to be excluded and C, you didn't make
anybody do any effort that wasn't necessary building a window in their
wall. Now I do have to tell you it's not so clear
to me why this issue about the בית התבן beit ha-teven was
a good example, because if as I just got through saying to
Michael, there was a house attached to it which made it consider
a legitimate place to leave over, then what, then what does it
bring a proof to? Then it was a place in theory could
have been included in the עירוב, Eruv, you know. So it's still
not exactly clear to me how it's similar, you know, in the
sense that, that if it had a house and it could have
been included in the עירוב Eruv and it was a house that
opened in the public space, and this case does not seem to
be that. This case it didn't open into the public space at
all. So I'm still not exactly clear about the proof, but at
least he was happy and he felt that was considered legitimate שיור.
shiur. So your question is do we do a שיור shiur nowadays
in terms of, do we ever make an עירוב Eruv around an
entire city? I guess Charlie said they once made, they made in
Manhattan that was done.
In Manhattan was done that they did an entire city.
The entire island for a while.
Well I guess one question would be is if you leave off
non-Jews, you know, from the עירוב, Eruv, you know, is that considered
a שיור? shiur? Well
that's, that's the big
question of how
you deal with the non-Jewish ownership and how that works.
Yeah, I don't know. It's an interesting question about practically how does
this ever play out if you actually wanted to do an entire
city.
And in fact in Israel that is done in most cities. There's
an עירוב Eruv around the entirety of ירושלים, Yerushalayim, for instance. What?
There's an עירוב Eruv around the entirety of ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Right. Right.
Which is now a city of more than 600,000, which is now...
Look, it could work that if you basically claim, if we make
an עירוב Eruv it means that for some way we're saying, I
said this yesterday, that we don't consider it to be 600,000, like
600,000 don't use the street every day, however we say that allows
us to make an עירוב Eruv and get around the 600,000 problem,
could allow us to say that we're not in the category of
עיר של רבים. Ir shel rabbim. But I would have to see
למעשה le-ma'aseh what actually said about that. Okay.
But that was not considered a problem then?
Well, that we don't have it on the entire city, right?
But we consider an entire city now, now, right.
Okay, so now let's, now let's continue. תניא אלא אם כן עשה
לה. Tanya ella im ken asah lah. אלא אם כן עשה לחוצה
לעיר חדשה. ella im ken asa le-chutzah la-ir chadashah. So this is
exactly this point about you have to leave off a section of
the city if it's an עיר של רבים. Ir Shel Rabbim. תניא,
אמר רבי יהודה, עיר אחת הייתה ביהודה, Tanya, amar Rabbi Yehuda, ir
achat hayetah bi-Yehuda, there was a city in Judea, וחדשה שמה, ve-Chadashah
shemah, its name was Chadashah. Now, by the way, if that sounds
weird, Tosafot and Rashi actually elsewhere quotes you a pasuk. Tosafot says
בספר יהושע היא כתיבה בנחלת יהודה. be-Sefer Yehoshua hi ketuvah be-nachalat Yehuda.
It actually is explicitly there's a city called Chadashah in the area
of Judea. Wow. Okay, so, yep, so והיו בו נון דיורין ve-hayu
vo nun diyorin and there were 50 people that lived in it,
אנשים ונשים וטף, anashim ve-nashim ve-taf, men, women, and children. So there,
as opposed to 600,000 which is a count of males, here it's
a count of the entire population. ובה היו משערים חכמים, u-vah hayu
mishaarim chachamim,
and that's what the Rabbis used as the model for the size
of an עיר של רבים Ir Shel Rabbim that you had to
leave over. והיא הייתה שיעור, ve-hi hayetah shiur, and that was what
was considered a שיעור, shiur,
an amount to leave over. איבעיא להו, Ibba'yu lehu, so they asked,
חדשה מהו? Chadashah mahu? What about the city of Chadashah itself? If
it wanted to make an עירוב, Eruv, and it was an עיר
של רבים, Ir Shel Rabbim, how what would it leave over? You
can't leave over yourself, let's say you're only that. Now, of course,
this really is a huge contradiction to Rashi that says עיר של
רבים Ir Shel Rabbim is 600,000, because now the Gemara wants to
know how what if Chadashah was an עיר של רבים, Ir Shel
Rabbim, how would you handle? It's 50 people! So maybe they had
such a huge market day that 600,000 people from all the neighboring
cities came once a week, but anyway, it's quite a contradiction to
that approach. Anyway, so the Gemara says חדשה כהיכי דהוי שיעור לגדולה,
Chadashah ke-heichi de-havei shiur le-gedolah, so first I'm sorry, so first the
Gemara
assumes that it means the section of the fifty people section in
a large city. What do they do? So Gemara says that's not
a
problem, חדשה כהיכי דהוי שיעור לגדולה, Chadashah ke-heichi de-havei shiur le-gedolah, the
same way this 50 person section is considered an excluded part for
the rest of the city, גדולה נמי הוי שיעור לקטנה. gedolah nami
havei shiur le-ktannah. So the rest of the city is the exception
for this little small section. So which is the point that you
can make an עירוב Eruv around all parts of the city as
long as it's not a unified עירוב. Eruv. Okay, so if you
leave off this section, so this section has excluded the major city,
and the major city is excluded this section, שלום על ישראל Shalom
Al Yisrael and it works. אלא, Ela, so the Gemara says, no,
no, here's the question: כעין חדשה מהו? ke-ein Chadashah mahu? If you
had something like this Chadashah, meaning a standalone city,
what would be the story? meaning if you have a city that's
only 50 people and you have to leave over 50 people, how
can you make an עירוב Eruv in that city? Right, assuming it's
an עיר של רבים. Ir Shel Rabbim. If it's not big enough,
essentially what he's saying is it's not big enough,
there's nobody to leave over. Right, if it was 51, then presumably
you could have the one guy by himself and the 50 guys
by themselves, right? If there's nobody to leave over, or actually no,
51 wouldn't work because according to this approach, any excluding part has
to be 50. So what happens if the thing is 50 or
less than a hundred, anyway? רב הונא ורב יהודה, חד אמר בעי
שיעור, Rav Huna ve-Rav Yehuda, chad amar ba'ei shiur, that would still
required and you'd be stuck essentially, or maybe I don't know, it's
not clear, maybe they would redefine what
a שיעור shiur would be, וחד אמר לא בעי שיעור. ve-chad amar
lo ba'ei shiur. No, that case you don't have to worry about
it because it's not so much of an עיר של רבים. Ir
Shel Rabbim. So again, that's pretty funny in making us think what
this עיר של רבים Ir Shel Rabbim is. רבי שמעון אומר ג'
חצרות. Rabbi Shimon omer: gimmel chatzerot. Rabbi Shimon says, no, you don't
have to leave over fifty people, just three courtyards with two houses
each. אמר רב חמא בר גוריא אמר רב, הלכה כרבי שמעון. Amar
Rav Chama bar Gurya amar Rav, halakhah ke-Rabbi Shimon. We rule like
Rabbi Shimon, that that's enough to leave over. רב יצחק אמר אפילו
בית אחד וחצר אחת. Rav Yitzchak amar: afilu bayit echad ve-chatzer achat.
Even one house and one courtyard. Doesn't have to be three courtyards
with two houses each, one house and one courtyard. So the Gemara
says חצר אחת סלקא דעתך? chatzer achat salka daatach? One courtyard by
itself? meaning they thought meant either a one house separate from a
courtyard. So what good is a courtyard if nobody's living on it?
What significance does it have? אלא אימא בית אחד בחצר אחת. Ela
eima: bayit echad be-chatzer achat. As long as you leave over one
house in one courtyard. So a unit of a courtyard and a
house, but it doesn't have to be three, it can be one.
אמר ליה אביי לרב יוסף, Amar leh Abaye le-Rav Yosef, so Abaye
said to Rav Yosef,
הא דרב יצחק, גמרא או סברא? ha de-Rav Yitzchak, gemara o sevara?
That idea of Rav Yitzchak, which he said one and one and
not three and three courtyards of two each, is that a tradition
he has, or is that just on his own like he's just
started saying his own logic? Logically this should be enough. Or is
it a tradition? So and Tosafot says part of the question is
he's arguing on a תנא. Tanna. There's no תנא Tanna that says
it, he's an אמורא, Amora, so maybe he has a tradition. Where's
he getting this from? אמר ליה, מאי נפקא מינה? Amar leh: mai
nafka minah? What do you care? meaning what difference does it make?
It's his position, what do you care if it's a סברא sevara
or if it's something that he thought up himself? אמר ליה, Amar
leh, he said back to him, this is the very famous line
of the Gemara, גמרא גמור זמורתא היא? gemara gmur zmoreta hi? You
know, basically you learn your teaching and it should just be like
a song? So which also, by the way, reflects probably the reality
that in an oral culture, they would learn things with a sing-song
type of a melody. So anyway, meaning what are we supposed to
do, just like parrot what we're taught? You know, we I want
to understand where he's getting it from. So it's pretty
funny, of course it makes difference because if it's a position that
he arrived on on himself, it's more given for debate and analysis
and questioning, otherwise it's just a straight
teaching. Also, Tosafot points out if
it's a tradition, then you could understand. So תוספות Tosafos tries to
explain a little bit the back and forth and say that no
he wasn't challenging the actual הלכה. halacha. He was just saying like
theoretically it makes sense that one and one should be enough. So
that was the question then. Well if he's not actually challenging the
הלכה, halacha, he's just saying theoretically what do you care whether he
got that as a teaching, you know, as a tradition or whether
he said it on his own. And רמ"א Ramo says even if
it's only theoretical it still matters I want to understand you know
and it's important to understand. So it's very you know so so
anyway it is interesting that some ראשונים Rishonim do think it's a
הלכה halacha position and actually are somewhat inclined to rule that way.
Yes, Seth, what did you say? What were you going to what
you had a question? No? Okay. So fine that's the end of
the idea of leaving over. By the way I should say and
nobody asked me this yesterday and I don't know the answer so
I'm glad no one asked me it, what the heck is this
משנה mishna doing in this פרק? perek? The entire פרק perek is
about עירוב תחומין. eiruv techumim. All of a sudden dropped in the
middle of a פרק perek is עיר חדשה ir chadasha you know
I'm sorry עיר של רבים ir she-rabim עיר של יחיד ir she-yachid
one עירוב eiruv or multiple עירובים eiruvs which is all about עירוב
חצרות. eiruv chatzeros. And this משנה mishna we're back to עירוב תחומין.
eiruv techumim. So this will be like the little homework assignment for
you you can figure out what the heck this משנה mishna was
doing. But now we get back to what I consider the easier
part of עירובינג eiruving which is עירוב תחומין eiruv techumim not עירוב
חצרות. eiruv chatzeros. Let's look at this next משנה. mishna. מי שהיה
במזרח
ואמר לבנו, Mi she-hayah ba-mizrach ve-amar li-bno, somebody was in the east
and said to his son ערב לי במערב, arev li ba-ma'arav, this
was ערב שבת. erev shabbos. He said to his son go put
for me an עירוב eiruv in the west of the city. במערב
ואמר לבנו ערב לי במזרח Ba-ma'arav ve-amar li-bno arev li ba-mizrach or
he was in the west and told his son to do it
in the east. אם יש הימנו לביתו אלפים אמה Im yesh himenu
le-beito alpayim amah if from him to his house is 2000 אמות
amot ולאירובו יותר מכאן u-le-eiruvo yoter mikan but his עירוב eiruv is
more further away from him מותר לביתו ואסור לאירובו. mutar le-beito ve-asur
le-eiruvo. He can go back to his house but he can't go
to his עירוב. eiruv. So the point basically is
here's your house okay
your your here on שבת shabbos okay your I don't know 2000
exactly 2000 and but you told your son on ערב שבת erev
shabbos put me in make me an עירוב eiruv in the west.
Okay and you were here in the east so you can't get
to your עירוב. eiruv. So if this עירוב eiruv is effective you're
going to be considered חוץ לעירוב chutz la-eiruv you understand what
I'm saying that's more than 2000 אמות amot down.
Doesn't matter it's 2000 to the house whatever this is call it
a thousand doesn't matter it's 3000 between you and the עירוב eiruv
when שבת shabbos starts okay. By the way according to רש"י Rashi
and others it doesn't matter if you said it to your son
even if you did it yourself you put it here and then
you took a light a nice walk and found yourself 3000 אמות
amot away. So for this עירוב eiruv to get this עירוב eiruv
were to take effect you would be חוץ לעירוב chutz la-eiruv okay.
Now you could say okay fine so you're stuck you can't move
ארבע אמות arba amot you're חוץ לעירוב. chutz la-eiruv. But the but
we can but what we do say is since it would put
you חוץ לעירוב chutz la-eiruv this עירוב eiruv is not effective okay
the עירוב eiruv doesn't take effect. One way רש"י Rashi explains it
is if you remember there's an idea that when שבת shabbos begins
you have to in theory be able to access your עירוב eiruv
and was talked about like if it's locked up and this and
that well here you can't access your עירוב eiruv because you're more
than 2000 אמות amot away from it. So that's a way of
saying that the עירוב eiruv isn't valid. So since this would put
you חוץ לעירוב chutz la-eiruv the עירוב eiruv isn't valid and therefore
you're considered to start שבת shabbos in your natural place which is
your home. Okay now there are some times where your עירוב eiruv
isn't valid and you're only left with ארבע אמות. arba amot. But
רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafos both point out that this time it's
better because your your default is your home. If you're traveling on
the road in certain cases and you know you don't have an
עירוב eiruv you might be left with ארבע אמות arba amot if
you're חוץ לעירוב chutz la-eiruv and so on. But here once it's
not valid your default is back to your home which you are
within and therefore you have you're back to your home.
Certainly within if you're within 2000 אמות amot of your home.
Now it says like this what happens if לאירובו אלפים אמה ולביתו
יתר מכאן le-eiruvo alpayim amah u-le-beiso yeseir mikan
let's say to your to the עירוב eiruv you're within 2000 אמות
amot of the עירוב eiruv but you're more than 2000 אמות amot
from your home. Now how can that happen if they're all on
a line like this? How can you be closer to your עירוב
eiruv than your home? So the גמרא Gemara will discuss that but
for now we'll assume that's the case. אסור לביתו ומותר לאירובו assur
le-beiso u-mutar le-eiruvo then of course your עירוב eiruv is effective you're
within 2000 אמות amot of your עירוב eiruv so your עירוב eiruv
is effective and you can't get to your house because your house
is more than 2000 אמות amot away from you and away from
the עירוב eiruv but that's a simple point. If your עירוב eiruv
is within 2000 אמות amot it's effective. הנותן את עירובו בעיבורה של
עיר לא עשה ולא כלום Ha-noten es eiruvo be-iburo shel ir lo
asah velo klum if you put your עירוב eiruv within the עיבור
ibur pregnancy of the city you know extension of the city right
so here's your city right and you sort of did the whole
squaring off and then maybe according to some you might have added
seventy and two thirds according to רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir you also
add that that might also be עיבור ibur but regardless okay if
you put your עירוב eiruv anywhere here it's worthless right because if
it was in the city you would have gotten that space and
2000 אמות amot from the edges so putting it within those confines
doesn't do anything for you okay לא עשה ולא כלום. lo asah
velo klum. נתנו חוץ לתחום אפילו אמה אחת Nasno chutz la-tchum afilu
amah achas he put it outside the תחום tchum he means the
תחום tchum he means the city boundaries it doesn't mean the תחום
tchum okay then even one אמה amah מה שנשכר הוא מפסיד mah
she-niskar hu mafsid however if If you went ahead and you put
it even one אמה amah outside of the city boundaries, okay? What?
Outside of the squared off?
Outside of the squared off, right.
If you put one אמה amah here, then you get 2,000 אמות
amos here, okay? Now it assumes that the city counts for zero.
Okay, and that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to discuss. Okay,
since if you started in the city it counts for zero, if
you start outside it counts for zero, but that's not always going
to be the case. So you, so this gives it one, zero,
and then you have 1,999 there, right? Doesn't it count for four
אמות amos or something?
So that's תוספות Tosafos discusses.
תוספות Tosafos says, I don't get it, I thought it counted for
four אמות. amos. So he says, yeah, but if that counts for
four אמות, amos, then maybe you also get four אמות amos from
here before you start counting. תוספות Tosafos is a long תוספות Tosafos
tries to figure out is it exact, you know, if this counts,
does this count for four אמות, amos, does this count for zero?
And you know when you put it here, how many אמות amos
do you get before you start counting, is it, it doesn't really
exist. But for roughly it works. Every אמה amah you move here,
so this becomes 2,001 and this becomes 1,999 and so on, you
know, ad infinitum. So wait, where were you? You put your עירוב
eruv here. I don't care where you were, you put your עירוב
eruv here, one אמה amah outside.
In the other case, you put your עירוב eruv there and you
couldn't, yeah, but here you could.
Okay, so now let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. קסלקא
דעתך, kasalka deitach, we're assuming למזרח lemizrach means למזרח ביתו, lemizrach beiso,
למערב lemaarav למערב ביתו. lemaarav beiso.
It says you were to the east and your עירוב eruv was
to the west means you were to the east of your house
and the עירוב eruv was to the west of the house, right?
That's the simple read of the משנה. Mishnah. בשלמא הימנו לביתו אלפיים
אמה ועירובו יותר מכאן, bishlama heimenu lebeiso alpayim amah veeruvo yoser mikan,
I understand that there's 2,000 אמה amah to get back home but
your עירוב eruv is more than 2,000 אמה amah to the west,
משכחת לה, mishkachas lah, that you can find in these scenarios.
דמטי לביתו ולא מטי לעירובו, demati lebeiso velo mati leeruvo, you can
get to your house because that's 2,000 אמה amah away from you
but not to your עירוב eruv because your עירוב eruv is further
away.
אלא, ela, but how about the second case in the משנה? Mishnah?
הימנו לעירובו אלפיים אמה ולביתו יותר מכאן, heimenu leeruvo alpayim amah ulebeiso
yoser mikan, from you to your עירוב eruv is 2,000 אמה amah
but it's further than that to get to your house, היכי משכחת
לה? heichi mishkachas lah? How do you have that, right? If basically
it's relative to the house and says you're in the east and
put your עירוב eruv in the west, how could it be possible
that you could get to your עירוב eruv without getting to your
house, which is what the משנה Mishnah says? Okay, so אמר רבי
יצחק, amar Rabbi Yitzchak, מי סברת למזרח למזרח ביתו למערב למערב ביתו,
mi savras lemizrach lemizrach beiso lemaarav lemaarav beiso, when it says to
the east and west it doesn't mean relative to the house. What
does it mean? לא, lo, that's not what it means. למזרח למזרח
בנו למערב למערב בנו. lemizrach lemizrach beno lemaarav lemaarav beno. It means
to the east or west of your son.
Meaning, you know, you were here, whatever, you know, you
were somewhere, I don't know, what would be the scenario, yeah, you
were,
this is like I don't know, 3,000 אמות amos away, and you
told your son, you said go make for me למזרח, lemizrach, go
make for me an עירוב eruv in the west, but you meant
west relative to where your son was. So an עירוב eruv in
the west is, he made the עירוב eruv over here. Okay, is
that clear? Meaning you're all away so you can get to the
עירוב eruv because that's only 2,000 and you can't get to your
home which is a thousand. So it doesn't mean west of your
home, it means sort of west of where your son was. But
actually, you're actually closer to your עירוב eruv than you are to
your house. The next answer is a more elegant one. רבא בר
רב שילא אמר אפילו תימא למזרח למזרח ביתו למערב למערב ביתו. Rava
bar Rav Shila amar afilu seima lemizrach lemizrach beiso lemaarav lemaarav beiso.
It even works relative to the house. דקאי ביתו באלכסונא. dekai beiso
be'alchsona. But
it's at an angle. So basically, right, here you are,
your עירוב eruv is a straight line from you and that's 2,000
אמה. amah. Your house is between you and the עירוב eruv but
it's way over here, right? So that could be 3,000 אמה. amah.
So the עירוב eruv is put, like I did here, whatever, north
and south, but let's put, whatever, east-west. The עירוב eruv is put
north of the house, you're south of the house, and nevertheless the
עירוב eruv is closer to you than your house. Okay,
so therefore that's the case that yes, it could work and that
you still cannot, you can get to your עירוב eruv without getting
to your house. Okay, now we get to the much more interesting
halakhic issue about the city not counting against your 2,000 אמות, amos,
which is very relevant. If you find yourself outside city limits, does
the city count against you or not?
Let's keep on going. Okay, so נותן את עירובו בתוך עיבורה. nosen
es eruvo besoch ibburah. חוץ לתחום סלקא דעתך? chutz latchum salka deitach?
So first the גמרא Gemara says when it says if you put
it outside the תחום, tchum, everything you gain you lose. Can't literally
mean outside the תחום. tchum. Outside the תחום tchum means outside 2,000
אמה, amah, then you completely have lost the city and maybe you'll
be starting חוץ לעירוב. chutz la'eruv. So אלא אימא חוץ לעיבורה. ela
eima chutz le'ibburah. No, we don't mean outside the תחום, tchum, we
mean outside of the city, the city parameters. Okay. מה שנשכר הוא
מפסיד. mah sheniskar hu mafsid.
Anything you gain on one side you lose on the other. So
the גמרא Gemara says מה שנשכר ותו לא? mah sheniskar vesu lo?
What, you only lose what you gain and you don't lose anything
else? והתניא, vehasanya, we taught in a ברייתא, Baraisa, הנותן את עירובו
בתוך עיבורה של עיר. hanosen es eruvo besoch ibburah shel ir. So
it starts the same way. If you put your עירוב eruv within
the squared off part of the city, so לא עשה ולא כלום,
lo asah velo klum, it was completely ineffective. anyway it was in
the city and you were in the city. נתנו *nasnu* חוץ לעיבורה
של עיר *chutz le'ibura shel ir*, if you put it outside the
squared-off part of the city, אפילו אמה אחת *afilu ama achas*, even
just one אמה *ama*, משתכר אותה אמה *mistaker osa ama*, you gain
that אמה *ama*, ומפסיד את כל העיר כולה *umavsid es kol hair
kula*, and you lose the whole city מפני שמידת העיר עולה לו
במידת התחום *mipnei shemidas hair ola lo bimidas hatchum* because the city
now counts against your תחום *tchum*. Okay, so basically says if you
start in the city, it's your ארבע אמות amos *arba amos*. But
if you start outside the city, then the city is in your
ארבע אמות *arba amos*, so then you get 2001 אמות *amos* this
way, but you only but you have to stop right there, right,
because the city is not your ארבע אמות *arba amos* so you
lose a lot by going outside of the city limits, you lose
the entire city being not counting against you. So that's obviously a
very different position of the משנה mishnah *Mishna*. So you could say
they argue exactly about that point, but let's see what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* says. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לא קשיא *lo
kashya*, it's not difficult. כאן שכלתה מידתו בחצי העיר כאן שכלתה מידתו
בסוף העיר *kan shekalsa midaso bachatzi hair kan shekalsa midaso besof hair*.
So the difference is like this: does the city count against you
or not? If your 2000 if this if your 2000 אמות *amos*,
if your thing ends in the middle of the city, then you're
stuck, then the city counts against you and you only can get
as far as you can get. If, however, your 2000 אמות *amos*
is a very small city and your 2000 אמות *amos* get you
to the other side, then because it got you to the other
side, then it's all within your תחום *tchum*, then it counts as
zero. And then it doesn't count against you at all and you
get another 2000 אמות *amos* that way. Okay, so basically this idea
that the city count doesn't count against you when you start outside
is only for very small cities. It's only for cities less than
2000 אמות *amos*, which is basically a kilometer. I mean, for then
it might have been big cities, but for us it's really tiny.
Okay, so when the משנה mishnah *Mishna* says you gain one here
and you can go 1999 there, that's there from this one, after
going 2000 אמות *amos*, you can get across the whole city. If
that's true, then the city doesn't count against you as well. So
the city doesn't count against you when you start in it or
when you start outside of it, but it's within totally encompassed within
your תחום *tchum*. Otherwise, it counts against you. So the גמרא *Gemara*
says וכרב אידי *uchrav Idi*, like the position of רב אידי Rav
Idi, *Rav Idi*. דאמר רב אידי Rav Idi אמר רב יהושע בן
לוי *de'amar Rav Idi amar Rav Yehoshua ben Levi* היה מודד ובא
*haya moded uva*. You were measuring your 2000 אמות *amos*, like you
were just counting off paces. You found yourself outside of a city
and you were counting off paces to get your 2000 אמות *amos*.
It was שבת Shabbos *Shabbos* וכלתה מידתו בחצי העיר *vechalsa midaso bachatzi
hair*. And the 2000 paces stopped in the middle of a city.
אין לו אלא חצי העיר *ein lo ela chatzi hair*. You only
get the half of the city that was within your 2000 אמות
*amos*. The city counts against you. כלתה מידתו בסוף העיר *kalsa midaso
besof hair*. If however the 2000 paces got you to the end
of the city, it completely encompassed the city, then נעשית לו העיר
כולה כארבע אמות *nasais lo hair kula kearba amos*. Then it doesn't
count against you at all, it's only four אמות *amos* ומשלימין לו
את השאר *umashlimin lo es hashar* and you get all the rest.
Okay, so it really makes a huge difference. Once you can get
across the city, then it counted only for four אמות *amos*. But
if not, you're really stuck. So that's the explanation of the contradiction
of the ברייתא *Braisa* and the משנה *Mishna*. It's whether the city
is completely within your תחום *tchum* or not. אמר רב אידי *amar
Rav Idi*, so said רב אידי *Rav Idi*, אין אלו אלא דברי
נביאות *ein elu ela divrei nevi'os*. This is just like words of
prophecy. Now רש"י *Rashi* says that that's like a big put down,
which is like where the heck are you getting this? It's like
a, you know, if it's like God it's like an arbitrary distinction,
there's no logical basis here. If you look at רש"י *Rashi* he
says it well, he says it well three lines in wide lines.
אין אלו אלא דברי נביאות *ein elu ela divrei nevi'os* כנביא מפי
הגבורה שאינו נותן טעם לדבריו *kenavi mipi hagevura she'eino nosen ta'am lidvarav*,
like you're just speaking ex cathedra, you're not giving any reason, and
you know like a נביא *navi* has no weight in a discussion
of תורה שבעל פה *Torah shebe'al peh*. So אמרה יהושע לוי לדברים
אלו *amra Yehoshua Levi lidvarim elu*. ואי לא דגמיר לה מרביה לא
הוה אמר כי האי מילתא בלא טעמא *ve'i lo degamir lah merabeih
lo hava amar ki hai milsa belo ta'ama*. It must be that
he has a tradition because I don't see any logic to this
thinking. תוספות *Tosafos*, that's what רש"י *Rashi* says, and that works in
a lot of contexts. אין אלו אלא דברי נביאות *ein elu ela
divrei nevi'os* is like a real put down. תוספות *Tosafos* actually says
that it's a compliment. It's like, oh
my god, that was like a רוח הקודש *ruach hakodesh* distinction. Okay,
so it's an interesting question about the whole, you know, at about
this phrase. I mean everybody sort of does agree that דברי נביאות
*divrei nevi'os* doesn't really work in a תורה שבעל פה *Torah shebe'al
peh* discussion. Yeah, well the גמרא *Gemara*'s not done. אין אלו אלא
דברי נביאות *ein elu ela divrei nevi'os*. This is nothing but like
words of prophecy. מה לי כלתה בחציה מה לי כלתה בסופה *mah
li kalsa bachatzya mah li kalsa besofa*. What difference does it make?
Either the city counts against you or it doesn't count against you.
Once if you can get into the city then we should either
say it always counts against you or it never does, but what's
this type of a distinction? So אמר רבא *amar Rava*, so רבא
*Rava* said, אטו ברייתא תניא *atu Braisa tanya*, what are you what
are you so upset about? Both are our משניות mishnayos. *Mishnayos*, this
idea, this difference, that we could infer at least from משניות *Mishnayos*.
What does the משנה *Mishna* say? אנשי עיר גדולה anshei ir gedolah
מהלכין את כל עיר קטנה ואין אנשי קטנה מהלכין את כל עיר
גדולה *anshei ir gedola mahalchin es kol ir ktana ve'ein anshei ktana
mahalchin es kol ir gedola*. The people of a big city can
do the small one, and the small one can't do the big
one. So what does this mean? So we're assuming what it means
is that here you have a big city that's I don't know
let's say three— 3,000 אמות by 3,000, and here you have right
next door a small little city that’s, I don’t know, 500 by
500. So these people who start here, this whole city counts as
nothing, right? And therefore, they can go, right, a thousand—let’s say a
thousand אמות—outside of their city, and they can go the whole 500
and another 500. So they can go through the entire small city.
Yeah, but the people of the small city, this counts as nothing,
so they go a thousand, but then they have to stop in
the middle of the big city. They can’t go through the whole
big city. Okay, so basically, exactly makes the point that the city
you start in doesn’t count against you, but a city you go
into does count against you. One minute. Okay, so you see there’s
an idea that sometimes our משנה says the city doesn’t count against
you, but this משנה makes it implicit, implicit, that the city does
count against you. So what are you going to do? So clearly
there’s a distinction. מאי טעמא, mai ta’ama, what’s the reason the people
of the small city can’t do the big city? לאו משום, lav
mishum, isn’t it not דהני כלהו מידתם בחצי העיר והני כלהו מידתם
בסוף העיר, de-hani kalsu midasom ba-chatzi ha-ir ve-hani kalsu midasom be-sof ha-ir,
that one of them their—you know, their measurement goes only to the
middle of the city, the other it goes through the whole city?
By the way, I made a mistake, because once here they can
do—this is included within their
2,000—then they get another thousand, and this doesn’t count for anything. Okay,
but anyway, you see that if you’re in the—if you get stuck
in the middle of a city, you’re stuck; you don’t get the
whole city. So רב אידי, so why did רב אידי not consider
that an evidence that you don’t get stuck in the middle of
a city? אנשי אנשי תני. anshei anshei tani. He doesn’t say אנשי
עיר גדולה anshei ir gedolah can go, but ואין אנשי עיר קטנה,
ve-ein anshei ir ketanah, and the people of the—of the small city
cannot go. He said both the people of the big city can
go and the people of the small city can go. It’s a
question of the text, right? Our text is אנשי עיר גדולה anshei
ir gedolah can go ואין אנשי עיר קטנה ve-ein anshei ir ketanah
go. He said אנשי עיר גדולה can go and אנשי עיר קטנה
anshei ir ketanah can go; they can both go. Okay, ומוקי לה
u-mokei lah and he says it, ומוקי לה בנסוין, u-mokei lah bi-nesuyin,
that what it’s talking about is that you actually
put your עירוב eiruv in the other city. ומוקי לה בנסוין. u-mokei
lah bi-nesuyin. אבל מודה לו, aval modeh lo, but okay, then the
גמרא is going to go on אבל מודה לו תנא. aval modeh
lo tanna.
So he basically says, no, that’s not the scenario.
It’s saying that the people of the small can go in the
big, not cannot go, and the people of the big can go
in the small; they get the whole thing. And what it means
is that you just wanted to join and be part of the
other city. So here you’re person A, you wanted to put your
עירוב eiruv in city A, and then you get the whole city,
and then you can—you know, so you can go the whole city
if you decide to start שבת in the whole city. And if
you’re B and you put your עירוב eiruv here in there, then
you get to be part of that city and you can go
the whole city. So basically, it is not talking about the difference
about whether it goes halfway or not halfway. It says there are
scenarios, you can basically switch which city your allegiance is to, but
it’s really not at all relevant, relevant to our discussion. So we
will continue to see tomorrow where the גמרא is going to stick
by this distinction about whether if it ends in the middle you’re
stuck, or if it goes the whole way it doesn’t count against
you at all. It’s going to hold on to that distinction and
try to continue to prove it from various
משניות. Okay, so more tomorrow, yeah.